<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nosql on Into The Void</title>
    <link>https://intothevoid.github.io/tags/nosql/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nosql on Into The Void</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 09:51:13 +1030</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://intothevoid.github.io/tags/nosql/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>NoSQL Databases - MongoDB</title>
      <link>https://intothevoid.github.io/2022/12/nosql-databases-mongodb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 09:51:13 +1030</pubDate>
      <guid>https://intothevoid.github.io/2022/12/nosql-databases-mongodb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;NoSQL databases are a type of database that is designed to handle large amounts of data that is distributed across a large number of servers. NoSQL databases are particularly well-suited for handling unstructured data, such as text, images, and videos, and for handling data that is generated by web and mobile applications.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are several different types of NoSQL databases, including:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Document databases: These databases store data in the form of documents, which are similar to JSON objects. Document databases are designed to be flexible and scalable, and they are often used for storing large amounts of data that is not well-suited to the tabular structure of a traditional relational database. Examples of document databases include MongoDB, Apache Cassandra, Couchbase, and Amazon DocumentDB.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Key-value stores: These databases store data as a collection of keys and values. Key-value stores are very fast and scalable, but they do not offer the same level of querying and indexing capabilities as other types of NoSQL databases. Examples of key-value stores include Redis and DynamoDB.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Column-family databases: These databases store data as a collection of columns, rather than rows. Column-family databases are highly scalable and are often used for storing large amounts of data that needs to be accessed and processed quickly. Examples of column-family databases include Apache Cassandra and Google BigTable.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Graph databases: These databases store data as a network of nodes and edges, which can be used to represent complex relationships between data items. Graph databases are often used for storing and querying data that has complex relationships, such as social networks or recommendation systems. Examples of graph databases include Neo4j and TigerGraph.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the main benefits of NoSQL databases is their ability to scale horizontally, meaning that they can easily add more servers to the database cluster as the amount of data or number of users increases. This makes them well-suited for handling the high volume of data and traffic that is common in modern web and mobile applications. NoSQL databases are also generally easier to set up and maintain than traditional relational databases, which can require more complex schema design and administration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
