<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Into The Void</title>
    <link>https://intothevoid.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Into The Void</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 23:07:51 +1030</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://intothevoid.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Crash Course in Rust</title>
      <link>https://intothevoid.github.io/2022/12/crash-course-in-rust/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 23:07:51 +1030</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://intothevoid.github.io/2022/12/crash-course-in-rust/</guid>
      <description>A crash course in Rust This article is a crash course in Rust programming and its setup / usage. For a more detailed guide check out -
Rust Book https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/book/ Rust By Example https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/rust-by-example/ Introduction to Rust: This lesson would cover the basics of Rust, including its history, features, and the benefits of using it.
Setting up a development environment: This lesson would explain how to install Rust on your computer and set up a development environment, including a code editor and any necessary tools and libraries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transfer Files from iOS to Linux wirelessly</title>
      <link>https://intothevoid.github.io/2022/08/transfer-files-from-ios-to-linux-wirelessly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2022 09:29:40 +0930</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://intothevoid.github.io/2022/08/transfer-files-from-ios-to-linux-wirelessly/</guid>
      <description>Overview I was an Android user for a long period of time, right from the Jellybean and Gingerbread days. After almost a decade being with Android I finally moved to iOS, because I was sick of the fragmentation and I wish Android took privacy as seriously as iOS does. One of the most common things I need to do is transfer files across from my iOS device to my Linux laptop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vim (Astro Vim) setup on a Macbook</title>
      <link>https://intothevoid.github.io/2022/07/vim-astro-vim-setup-on-a-macbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 11:53:48 +0930</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://intothevoid.github.io/2022/07/vim-astro-vim-setup-on-a-macbook/</guid>
      <description>Overview Use the following steps to have a decent vim installation relatively quickly on a Macbook with a M1 / M2 chipset
Brew installation Brew is a package manager for MacOS which makes it very easy to install packages. I highly recommend this package manager on MacOS. Its worth the effort to get it installed you will thank yourself later on.
From www.brew.sh -
/bin/bash -c &amp;#34;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh)&amp;#34; Sample command using brew -</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create a blog using Hugo and Github Pages</title>
      <link>https://intothevoid.github.io/2021/04/create-a-blog-using-hugo-and-github-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 14:13:49 +0930</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://intothevoid.github.io/2021/04/create-a-blog-using-hugo-and-github-pages/</guid>
      <description>Update: Added section on adding Github Action for Hugo build
This is a guide on how you can create a blog or website from scratch using Hugo and Github. This is also my first post on this blog, which has been created using the steps mentioned in this article using Hugo and Github Pages.
It is quite easy to create a blog using Wordpress or some other CMS but the simplicity of Hugo is what drove me to it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
